okay
let's talk about why we make bad decisions
so if you're like me then
you've probably been in that situation
where it's the end of the day or it's the morning
and you're thinking like okay
I'm gonna make a solid plan for myself
today I'm gonna be disciplined
I'm gonna come home from work
and I'm gonna get all these errands done
and I'm gonna treat myself really well
I'm gonna make a nice healthy proper meal
I'm gonna go to the gym afterwards I'm gonna exercise
and then maybe when I come home
I'll like start reading a book or something
I'll do something a little different
something that makes me feel like
I'm gonna advance my life in a new positive direction
this is our real life volition
and it's there to lead you on your way to making good life decisions
but this doesn't always work out that way
sometimes you get to the end of the day
and you realise that you haven't been very disciplined at all
a lot of those errands are still incomplete or like half started
we didn't end up going to the gym
and instead of making a proper meal
we've ordered some definitely not healthy take out food
and instead of reading that book
maybe you end up watching a show you've already seen
and we've not advanced our life
in a positive meaningful direction in any way at all
what is happening here
why would we ignore the voice of volition
that's telling us to do all of these beneficial positive things
well it could be a lot of things honestly
and definitely having like a mental health diagnosis
is going to amplify this problem a lot more
but even for the average person
this happens like pretty often
I mean it certainly happens to me
so what I wanted to share with you today
is a framework for understanding why this problem happens
and what we can actually do about it
this is a real problem that actually comes up in my work as a therapist kind of often
and I have really enjoyed seeing it demonstrated so clearly
and given such a unique role within the structure of a game like Disco Elysium has
so okay
there is a reason that we do not always follow the voice of volition
and go through with our good intentions
and it has to do with something called *psychological friction*
so in this context friction is
any force either internal or external
which opposes a behavioral change
so what do we know about regular friction right
if I am standing on an ice rink
and I move my body weight around a little bit
I'm going to start sliding around on the ice
there's not a lot of friction
between me and the surface that's under me
when I step off the ice
and now I'm standing on concrete
when I shift myself around I don't move right
there is a lot more friction between me and the ground
and psychologically
this principle is basically the same thing
if you imagine you're trying to do something
it's going to be much harder if there is more friction
between you and the process
and it's going to be much easier
if there is less friction
when friction is introduced
and we'll talk about what kinds of friction
are very common
the process tends to slow down
we tend to have a harder time
actually completing the thing we're trying to do
and it's much more likely that we're going to give up
when there is less friction
or we find a way to reduce the friction that's there
the process can start to speed up again
and will find more motivation
to actually keepworking on it
and really we can kind of think of this how habits work right
when you're trying to do something new
it can be hard to stay motivated and be consistent
and be very disciplined in it
we have to be very rigorous and consistent with things
before they start to get easier
and we have to do less work to get ourselves in the mindset to do it
like if we're trying to start you know an exercise regiment or something
so there's a lot of friction
between us and this new behavioral change
things start to get easier
when we learn more about that process
and we start developing sort of like the mental tricks
to get ourselves into that kind of mode
where we want to do it
we don't have to convince ourselves anymore
and our stamina to like do the thing that's difficult starts to go up
and
there is a lot less friction here
we start to develop that habit
when the process becomes streamlined and simplified
and we have to do less of the psychological work
to get ourselves moving on it
so basically
the things that we tend to do the most
and the patterns of behavior that we tend to repeat
are those where the amount of friction between us and the process is very minimal
so this is part of why
when we tell ourselves
we're going to do all these nice things
a lot of friction tends to get introduced in that process
because thinking about doing all those things isn't really that hard
but when it comes down to it
it takes an extra layer of scheduling and timing
and trying to like balance your energy throughout the day
you better make sure that you slept enough
ate well enough that your hydrated
that you actually have the motivation at the time you're trying to do that thing
to actually start it
honestly like at the end of a long day
we're not typically still in the high motivation state
that we were at the beginning of the day
when volition was telling us
how awesome we're gonna be sometime later
we are not always interested or capable
sometimes of fighting against all of the friction
that has found us along the way
so we choose things that are less difficult right
the kinds of habits that we have already formed
that we know work
that don't require a lot of mental fortitude to carry out
volition asks us to do things which are good for us
but that they are difficult to accomplish
and so it's often the voices of half light or electrochemistry
that give us other options
and don't ask us to fight against a bunch of friction
they just want us to chase whatever
impulse makes sense in the moment
you should tell people to off more often
I should I should do that I
No you shouldn't you're an officer of the law
maybe I shouldn't
so this has been really fascinating to see portrayed in Disco Elysium
because in my playthrough
I've been kind of role playing
and demonstrating this whole problem right
and so sometimes
volition will chime in with a thought
and I just ignore it and I go do something that
for a lot of people
looks like it's not really within my character's best interest
and they're right
but that's how people are
we are kind of walking contradictions
we just don't always act in our own best interests
like I said
even though the thought to do something good is available to us
that doesn't mean we're actually going to do it
in fact
we're very keenly aware a lot of the times
that we are doing something that's not in our best interest
and we're pulling the ice cream out of the fridge
and telling ourselves along the way
I really shouldn't
but I'm gonna anyway
so this is a real problem right
and the game is so good at demonstrating this
so what do you do about this right
I like the word friction
because it gives us a very easy framework to understand
and so when I'm working with someone who is struggling with motivation
or a lot of times were sort of questioning
like I'm very passionate about this thing
but I don't find myself doing it a lot
like I don't know what's wrong with me
maybe I've lost interest in it
that's where we may start to ask the question
okay well what kind of friction is in this process for you
and how might we start to work to reduce it
and the best place to start is actually trying to understand
whether this friction is even real or not
because that's the thing
there is real psychological friction and perceived psychological friction
now
that is not to say that friction by itself is a bad thing
in fact there are some cases
where introducing friction to some sort of behavioral process
is actually a good thing
think about an addiction for example right
which is a big part of disco elysium
where the habit to seek and use a substance
has become very normalized for us
and we're always looking to have the least amount of friction
between us and continuing that substance use
and so actually when you're trying to
work on breaking a habit
or lower the chances that an addiction develops
you actually want to introduce friction to the process
essentially making things harder is going to slow down
and may completely interrupt the process that we are trying to change
this is why when people are trying to quit a substance
they typically go to a detox center
and then they go into full rehabilitation
and that's to like completely separate themselves from
the environment and all of the social and psychological issues
which made repeating that pattern of behavior very easy
we want to introduce a ton of friction to this person's life temporarily
so that we can learn to develop better strategies
to cope with the issues that resulted in some sort of addiction
so this was all like pretty well demonstrated in my own play through
in which we spent ... a lot of time
trying to find a way to buy a pack of cigarettes
and I was explaining how
when we have a chemical dependence on something
like we are often going to prioritize that over most other things right
higher order things like solving a crime
or strengthening our relationships
and so the thought pattern may have been something like
okay well
our character wants to smoke
how do I do that
what's the simplest path here
I want to find the way with the least amount of friction
like I need this *now*
so we go into Frittte and Frittte girl is there okay
and she tells us that
we don't have the money for cigarettes
there's a way that we can get the money for cigarettes
what we can do is we can collect tare and tare is trash
and so what we can do is try to find a bag
so that we can pick up all the tear in Revachol
and we'll spend as much time as we need to collecting this
so that we can go and buy the cigarettes
and that sounds like kind of a difficult drawn out process
and it was
however there was less friction in doing that
than there would be if I tried to solve this murder
without the stimulant that my body is craving
I may have been telling myself like
look this whole detective thing is just way too hard without a buzz right
there's too much friction
I can't talk to people I can't think straight right
I'm gonna do this other thing that's still difficult
but maybe it will help like reduce
the amount of friction in this other bigger more difficult task
and then we'll go do it
and that is an example of totally made up perceived fake friction right
like smoking cigarettes doesn't actually make us a better detective
like it gives us a maybe a false sense of plus 1 to our intellect
but we may have convinced ourselves
as you know
many people who are struggling with substances do
that we are inadequate or unable to perform a certain task without this thing
and so
like we look at that and say no there's too much friction
I can't do that it's too hard
having this substance will make it easier
when really what we have done is just choose something that's equally hard
and we're reinforcing a bad pattern of behavior
and one that's pretty bad for us
so that was a demonstration of the perceived kind of friction right
and then this happened again
nearing the end of our first day in Revachol
in which my character had
also been searching for ways to drink alcohol
and so we come to the end of the day
and we hadn't really found any opportunities to do that
besides like licking some alcohol off of a table
but so we're standing there at the end of the day
and we're talking to Garte
who is the manager of the whirling in rags
and we're asking him
like can I buy a drink
look I've had a long day okay
I spent most of it looking for cigarettes
and then I did a little bit of detective work
and it has tired me out okay
now I need the other substance that I'm depended on
to sleep all of this off
and that's when Gart tells us like dude I'm not the bartender okay
I don't actually serve drinks here
find another way to get drunk
you know what
the impact of rejection is stronger than than
the impulse to drink from my guy right now
as a sorry cop
I abandon I'm going to abandon the desire to drink
because I am too ashamed to ask further
he effectively made it
more difficult for us to do this
and
in my mind and in simulating the characters perspective
like we decided that this was just too much work right
like we're already tired enough
who knows how much more time and effort and money this was gonna take
to get some alcohol right
and so we gave up
there was too much friction introduced to the process
it would involve talking to people
it would have involved budgeting
it would have involved embarrassing ourselves even more
and so with a lot of friction introduced to the process
this slowed down and has the potential to completely interrupt the problem behavior
so I just find this whole thing fascinating
that the voice of volition represents
what is in real life
our good intentions to make healthy balance decisions for ourselves
and yet
typically
the things that it wants us to do require a lot of effort
a lot of deep behavioral changes
and there are often a lot of barriers in between us and doing them
and here you have like other voices
which have not so great intentions for us
in competition with volition
and there's way less friction involved in those
and so we chase those impulses
even though we know we shouldn't
that is just real life
and I love disco elysium for this
it's been one of my favorite parts of the game so far
so
what can you take away from this well
consider a change that you've been trying to make recently
or a habit that you're trying to break
and ask yourself
what is the friction involved in this process right
what is making it hard for me to make this good change
and is that a real source of friction
or is it one that I'm kind of like perceiving
because at the end of the day
we choose to ignore volition even though we know it's there
and that it actually wants something better for us
I genuinely think that
making a change is not always about working harder at something
in fact a lot of times
I think it's about making the process easier right
simpler streamlined
with the least amount of friction
and you may find that over time
just like any other habit
the more you train yourself to
detect and resolve the sources of friction in your life
you actually find it a little easier to listen to volition
when it talks to you
so
that is why we ignore volition in real life
I am very curious to hear what all of you think about this
and if there's anything that you can think of
that is a source of friction in your life
that you may not even even really known is there
so far Disco Elysium has been amazing
at like bringing together real mental health with practical game mechanics
and I find that really fun to talk about
so I'm also curious if there are other games and other systems in them
that you think would be worthy of this kind of analysis as well
who knows
maybe this could be like a series or something
where we talk about like the crossover between game design and mental health
and how mechanics can represent real cognitive structures
that we use and deal with every day
so thank you for watching my video
I hope you enjoyed it
yeah let me know if you'd like to hear more
of this kind of discussion with other game mechanics
and if you want to see more of where these ideas are kind of taking shape
and the discussions we're having about them
we're currently uploading a full let's play of Disco Elysium
with lots of psychological analysis
intermixed in that
so subscribe
if you want to catch those as the release or other standalone analyses like this one
猫猫打闹
right now these two are the friction between me and finishing this video
it's okay I love them
so with that said I will see you guys next time
I'm gonna go try to make some of my own good decisions right now